<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<style_reference>

  <source>Kurzgesagt — "The Coronavirus Explained &amp; What You Should Do" (YouTube)</source>

  <purpose>
    Read these paragraphs for prose style only. The subject matter is irrelevant.
    What to absorb: how a sequence of events is written as a sequence of short moves,
    how parallel sentence structures build escalation without raising the voice, how a
    concrete analogy replaces an abstract explanation, and how logical consequence is
    stated directly without softening. Do not write about viruses, immune cells, or
    pandemics. Only the sentence rhythm and the cause-to-consequence pattern are the reference.
  </purpose>

  <warning>
    Sentence lengths in these examples run longer than Readlock's ~14-word target (some reach 20+ words). This is because the source is a video script, written for audio, not swipe reading. Do NOT copy sentence length. Copy only the technique named in each paragraph's note.
  </warning>

  <paragraphs>

    <paragraph>
      <note>Sequence writing at its cleanest. Each sentence is one step. The verbs carry everything. The last sentence ("self-destruct") lands hard because every sentence before it was quiet.</note>
      <text>Even just a few corona viruses can cause quite a dramatic situation. The lungs are lined with billions of epithelial cells. These are the border cells of your body, lining your organs and mucosa waiting to be infected. Corona connects to a specific receptor on its victim's membranes to inject its genetic material. The cell, ignorant of what's happening, executes the new instructions, which are pretty simple: copy and reassemble. It fills up with more and more copies of the original virus until it reaches a critical point and receives one final order, self-destruct. The cell sort of melts away, releasing new corona particles ready to attack more cells.</text>
    </paragraph>

    <paragraph>
      <note>Parallel structure used to escalate. "First... The other..." builds a list that tightens. The final sentence repeats the structure three times in a row, which drives the point home without commentary.</note>
      <text>Two kinds of cells in particular wreak havoc. First, neutrophils, which are great at killing stuff, including our cells. As they arrive in their thousands, they start pumping out enzymes that destroy as many friends as enemies. The other important type of cells that go into a frenzy are killer T-cells, which usually order infected cells to commit controlled suicide. Confused as they are, they start ordering healthy cells to kill themselves too. The more and more immune cells arrive, the more damage they do, and the more healthy lung tissue they kill.</text>
    </paragraph>

    <paragraph>
      <note>Contrast stated as two sentences. No argument, no elaboration. The shape of the future depends on one variable, named plainly. The stakes are not dramatised — they are measured.</note>
      <text>There are two futures for a pandemic like Corona: fast and slow. Which future we will see depends on how we all react to it in the early days of the outbreak. A fast pandemic will be horrible and cost many lives; a slow pandemic will not be remembered by the history books.</text>
    </paragraph>

    <paragraph>
      <note>Logical escalation: one fact leads to the next, each sentence tightening the consequence. "Why is this so bad?" is the only rhetorical question and it answers itself in the next breath. Notice no sentence hedges.</note>
      <text>The worst case scenario for a fast pandemic begins with a very rapid rate of infection because there are no counter measures in place to slow it down. Why is this so bad? In a fast pandemic, many people get sick at the same time. If the numbers get too large, health care systems become unable to handle it. There aren't enough resources, like medical staff or equipment like ventilators, left to help everybody. People will die untreated. And as more health care workers get sick themselves, the capacity of health care systems falls even further.</text>
    </paragraph>

    <paragraph>
      <note>A concrete analogy replaces a paragraph of chemistry. "A layer of fat" is the anchor. The jalapeño line is the sharpest analogy in the script — one image, no explanation needed. Notice how the mechanism is stated before the analogy, not after.</note>
      <text>Although it sounds trivial, the very best thing you can do is to wash your hands. The soap is actually a powerful tool. The corona virus is encased in what is basically a layer of fat; soap breaks that fat apart and leaves it unable to infect you. It also makes your hands slippery, and with the mechanical motions of washing, viruses are ripped away. To do it properly, wash your hands as if you've just cut up some jalapeños and want to put in your contact lenses next.</text>
    </paragraph>

  </paragraphs>

</style_reference>
