<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rlockie_format_guide>

  <meta>
    <title>.rlockie Syntax Reference</title>
    <related_files>
      <file name="ReadlockCopywritingGuide.md" role="content authority (tone, voice, phase structure, lengths, all writing rules)" />
      <file name="ReadlockFinalTest.xml" role="rule checklist, run after writing" />
      <file name="ReadlockBlacklist.xml" role="banned AI writing patterns" />
    </related_files>
    <authority_note>This file defines how .rlockie files are structured: what blocks exist, what fields each block needs, and how to format them. It is NOT the content authority. For tone, voice, register, phase structure, swipe length, consequence/hint rules, reflect content, color highlight meanings, and every other "what do I actually write" question, the authority is ReadlockCopywritingGuide.md. If anything here contradicts the copywriting guide, the copywriting guide wins.</authority_note>
  </meta>

  <contents>
    <item id="1">Metadata writing rules</item>
    <item id="2">Document structure</item>
    <item id="3">@course</item>
    <item id="4">@segment</item>
    <item id="5">@package</item>
    <item id="6">Content blocks: @text, @question, @true_false, @estimate, @quote, @pause, @reflect</item>
    <item id="7">Formatting rules</item>
    <item id="8">Comments</item>
  </contents>

  <section id="1" name="Metadata writing rules">
    <description>The copywriting guide covers @text, @question, and other content blocks. Metadata fields (title, description, author, segment titles) are not covered by that guide, but they must follow the same register.</description>

    <principle>Write metadata the way a person would describe a book to a friend, not the way a marketing team would pitch it to investors.</principle>

    <example type="bad">Explore the fascinating world of cognitive biases and unlock powerful psychological principles that will transform your design thinking.</example>
    <example type="good">How cognitive biases shape the way people interact with designed objects.</example>

    <example type="bad">A comprehensive deep dive into the art and science of color theory.</example>
    <example type="good">Why colors make people feel, and how designers have used that for centuries.</example>

    <rules>
      <rule>Every rule in ReadlockCopywritingGuide.md Sections 2 and 4 applies to metadata as well (banned verbs, banned openers, banned closers, banned inflators, casual slang, em dashes, triple-anything lists).</rule>
      <rule>Descriptions state what the course is about. They do not sell it.</rule>
      <rule>Segment titles are short, plain nouns or noun phrases ("Foundations," "Perception and Decisions"). Not taglines.</rule>
      <rule>If a sentence could appear in any course about any topic and still make sense, it is too generic. Rewrite it to be specific to this course.</rule>
    </rules>
  </section>

  <section id="2" name="Document structure">
    <description>A .rlockie file has three levels of hierarchy:</description>

    <hierarchy>
      <level depth="0" declaration="@course" note="exactly once, first line of the file" />
      <level depth="1" declaration="@segment" note="one or more, groups packages into chapters" />
      <level depth="2" declaration="@package" note="one or more per segment, separates lessons" />
      <level depth="3" declaration="@text" note="content block" />
      <level depth="3" declaration="@question" note="content block" />
      <level depth="3" declaration="@true_false" note="content block" />
      <level depth="3" declaration="@estimate" note="content block" />
      <level depth="3" declaration="@quote" note="content block" />
      <level depth="3" declaration="@pause" note="content block" />
      <level depth="3" declaration="@reflect" note="content block" />
    </hierarchy>

    <rules>
      <rule>Every line that starts with @ is a DECLARATION. It must appear on its own line with nothing else on that line.</rule>
      <rule>Everything that follows a declaration (until the next @declaration) is that block's BODY.</rule>
    </rules>
  </section>

  <section id="3" name="@course">
    <description>Must be the very first line. Followed by course metadata as key: value pairs.</description>

    <template>
@course

id: [course identifier]
language: [two-letter uppercase language code, e.g. EN]
title: [course display title]
author: [author display name]
description: [one-line description]
color: [one of the 12 allowed swatches, e.g. 8461BD — NO leading #]
genres: [3 to 5 comma-separated keys from the closed list, e.g. design, psychology, productivity]
relevant_for: [comma-separated keys from the closed list: designers, product-managers, founders, engineers, writers, marketers, leaders, investors, students, anyone]
    </template>

    <rules>
      <rule>All eight fields are required.</rule>
      <rule>One blank line between @course and the first field.</rule>
      <rule>language is a two-letter uppercase code (e.g. EN, PL, DE). Defaults to EN when omitted.</rule>
      <rule>description must be a single line.</rule>
      <rule>color must be exactly one of these 12 hex values, WITHOUT a leading "#": 9E7071, D0CBD6, C78871, FAF0A2, 8461BD, 78A3ED, 72ACAD, C85159, 6D7487, CAC7EE, 6A99D4, FFC1E2. The "#" is never written in the .rlockie file (e.g. "color: 8461BD", not "color: #8461BD"). Pick the swatch closest to the original book cover when available; otherwise pick the swatch that best fits the topic's mood. Never invent a new hex value.</rule>
      <rule>genres must contain 3 to 5 comma-separated tags drawn from this closed list ONLY: design, psychology, business, technology, self-help, science, philosophy, history, economics, leadership, creativity, productivity, communication, user-experience, product-development. Never invent a new genre. Pick the closest tag from the list instead of coining a new one.</rule>
      <rule>relevant_for values must come from the closed list: designers, product-managers, founders, engineers, writers, marketers, leaders, investors, students, anyone.</rule>
    </rules>

    <id_format>
      <description>The id follows the pattern: [type]:[kebab-case-title]-[4-char-hash]</description>
      <type name="book" description="for courses based on a book" example="book:thinking-fast-and-slow-xkfm" />
      <type name="topic" description="for courses about a standalone topic" example="topic:psychology-of-design-abwq" />
      <type name="article" description="for courses based on an article" example="article:cognitive-load-theory-plnz" />
      <rule>The 4-char hash is randomly generated from lowercase a-z.</rule>
      <rule>The kebab-case title is a shortened version of the course title, not the full title.</rule>
    </id_format>
  </section>

  <section id="4" name="@segment">
    <description>Defines a chapter/section. Body is exactly two lines.</description>

    <template>
@segment
[Segment Title]
[Symbol - 1 to 3 uppercase characters]
    </template>

    <rules>
      <rule>A course must have at least one segment.</rule>
      <rule>The symbol is a short abbreviation (e.g. "BD" for "Basic Design").</rule>
      <rule>Every segment must be followed by at least one @package.</rule>
    </rules>
  </section>

  <section id="5" name="@package">
    <description>Separates packages (lessons) within a segment. The lines immediately after @package (before the first content block) are package metadata.</description>

    <template>
@package
[Package display title]
Free

@text
...
    </template>

    <rules>
      <rule>The first non-empty line after @package is the package display title.</rule>
      <rule>If the word "Free" appears on its own line, the package is marked as free.</rule>
      <rule>Both are optional. If no title is provided, a default "Package N" is used.</rule>
      <rule>Every package must contain at least one content block.</rule>
      <rule>The title and Free flag must come before any @text, @question, or other content declarations.</rule>
    </rules>
  </section>

  <section id="6" name="Content blocks">

    <block name="@text">
      <description>A reading slide. Each line becomes a separate text segment displayed one at a time.</description>

      <template>
@text
First line shown to the learner.
Second line shown after the first.
A third line with a &lt;c:g&gt;highlighted topic term&lt;/c:g&gt;.
      </template>

      <line_rules ref="ReadlockCopywritingGuide.md, Section 2, Sentence construction">
        <rule>Each line is one on-screen segment.</rule>
        <rule>One sentence per line is the default, up to two sentences allowed when they read as a single beat, three is never allowed.</rule>
        <rule>Every line, whether one or two sentences, fits in about 16 words total.</rule>
      </line_rules>

      <color_markup ref="ReadlockCopywritingGuide.md, Section 5, Phase 4, Color highlights">
        <color tag="c:g" color="green" meaning="Marks the TOPIC of the current package (the concept, study, book, or effect the package is about)." />
        <color tag="c:r" color="red" meaning="Marks a WRONG thing stated inside the text (a misconception, a deliberately wrong statement the narrator is about to correct). Never on the topic, never on anything correct." />
      </color_markup>

      <image_link>
        <format>image-link: "[search description]"</format>

        <template>
@text
The water cycle is one of the most elegant systems on Earth.
image-link: "Water cycle diagram"
Look at the graphic.
        </template>

        <description>The description is used to search Wikimedia Commons. Write it like a librarian tagging a photograph, not like a designer describing a mockup.</description>

        <rules>
          <rule>Use broad, categorical terms that real photographs and diagrams are tagged with.</rule>
          <rule>Use the actual subject name, not a creative interpretation of it.</rule>
          <rule>Prefer nouns over adjectives. "Human eye anatomy diagram" not "detailed beautiful eye illustration."</rule>
          <rule>Add "diagram" or "photograph" when the type of image matters.</rule>
          <rule>Ask yourself: "Would a Wikipedia article plausibly use this image?" If yes, good.</rule>
        </rules>

        <examples>
          <example type="good">Human eye anatomy diagram</example>
          <example type="good">Color wheel primary secondary colors</example>
          <example type="good">Crowd of people in a city street</example>
          <example type="good">Gestalt principles proximity similarity diagram</example>
          <example type="good">Coffee shop menu pricing</example>
          <example type="bad" reason="does not exist on Wikimedia">A futuristic holographic brain with neural pathways glowing in blue</example>
          <example type="bad" reason="too specific, too stylized">Minimal flat illustration of cognitive load theory</example>
          <example type="bad" reason="abstract concept, not searchable">Beautiful sunset over the ocean representing peace</example>
          <example type="bad" reason="no real image matches this">An elegant visualization of the anchoring effect</example>
        </examples>

        <rule>When an image is included, refer to it in the surrounding text: "Look at the graphic" or "The diagram shows how..." Never leave an image floating without context.</rule>
      </image_link>

      <rules>
        <rule>At least one line of text.</rule>
        <rule>Color markup is rare: maximum 1 to 2 highlights per WHOLE PACKAGE across both colours combined, not per text block. Most @text blocks will contain zero highlights. The one that names the topic gets the green one.</rule>
        <rule>At most 1 color highlight per @text swipe. Do not put two highlights in the same swipe.</rule>
      </rules>
    </block>

    <block name="@question">
      <description>A single-choice or multiple-choice question.</description>

      <template>
@question
[Question text - one line]

answer: [First answer option]
consequence: [Feedback shown when this answer is picked]

answer: [Second answer option]
consequence: [Feedback shown when this answer is picked]

answer: [Third answer option]
consequence: [Feedback shown when this answer is picked]

correct_answers: [comma-separated 1-based indices, e.g. 1 or 1,3]
explanation: [Explanation shown after answering]
hint: [Hint shown before answering]
      </template>

      <rules>
        <rule>Question text must be exactly one line.</rule>
        <rule>Minimum 2 answers, maximum 3.</rule>
        <rule>Each answer must be immediately followed by its consequence.</rule>
        <rule>Blank line between each answer+consequence pair.</rule>
        <rule>correct_answers uses 1-based indexing (1 = first answer).</rule>
        <rule>Both hint and explanation are required.</rule>
        <rule ref="ReadlockCopywritingGuide.md, Section 5, Phase 3">Each consequence is 1 to 3 sentences, each sentence at most about 14 words (can go to 17-18).</rule>
        <rule ref="ReadlockCopywritingGuide.md, Section 5, Phase 3">Each hint is exactly one sentence, at most 14 words (can go to 17-18).</rule>
      </rules>
    </block>

    <block name="@true_false">
      <description>A statement the learner must judge as true or false. The two answer options are always literally "True" and "False" — never descriptive text.</description>

      <template>
@true_false
[Statement to evaluate]

true: [Consequence shown if the reader picks True]
false: [Consequence shown if the reader picks False]

correct_answers: [1 for true, 2 for false]
explanation: [Explanation text]
hint: [Hint text]
      </template>

      <rules>
        <rule>Statement must be exactly one line.</rule>
        <rule>Exactly one true: and one false: line, in that order.</rule>
        <rule>The two answer options are always literally "True" and "False". Never descriptive text, never paraphrased, never restating the statement.</rule>
        <rule>The text after true: and false: is the consequence shown after the reader picks that option, not the option label.</rule>
        <rule>correct_answers is 1 if the statement is true, 2 if false.</rule>
        <rule>hint is required, and follows the same rules as @question hints (one sentence, ~14 words).</rule>
        <rule>Consequences follow the same rules as @question consequences (1 to 3 sentences).</rule>
        <rule ref="ReadlockCopywritingGuide.md, Section 5, Phase 5">The statement should feel semi-obvious after a moment of thought, not a trap and not dumb.</rule>
      </rules>
    </block>

    <block name="@estimate">
      <description>A percentage estimation question. The learner drags a slider to guess.</description>

      <template>
@estimate
[Question asking for a percentage]
answer: [correct number, 0-100]
explanation: [Explanation]
hint: [Hint text]
      </template>

      <rules>
        <rule>Question must be exactly one line.</rule>
        <rule>answer must be an integer between 0 and 100.</rule>
        <rule>hint is required.</rule>
      </rules>
    </block>

    <block name="@quote">
      <description>A quote slide.</description>

      <template>
@quote
[The quote text]
[Author name - or leave empty]
      </template>

      <rules>
        <rule>First line is the quote (no quotation marks, the UI adds them).</rule>
        <rule>Second line is the author attribution. Can be left empty.</rule>
      </rules>
    </block>

    <block name="@pause">
      <description>A breather slide with a nice animation and a single sentence. Gives the reader a beat of rest between denser swipes.</description>

      <template>
@pause
[Single sentence]
      </template>

      <rules>
        <rule>Exactly one line, exactly one sentence. Never two.</rule>
        <rule>The sentence is a small interesting fact, observation, or reframing related to the topic of the package. Not trivia, not a quiz, not a recap, not a motivational line.</rule>
        <rule>Never starts with "Did you know...", "Fun fact:", or "Pro tip:".</rule>
        <rule ref="ReadlockCopywritingGuide.md, Section 5, @pause">Zero or one @pause per package. Default spot is after Phase 3 (questions), before Phase 4 (topic reveal). Must not name or hint at the topic.</rule>
      </rules>
    </block>

    <block name="@reflect">
      <description>A reflection prompt. Each line is one thinking point.</description>

      <template>
@reflect
[First thinking point, including one concrete example]
[Second thinking point, including one concrete example]
[Third thinking point, including one concrete example]
      </template>

      <rules>
        <rule>2 to 3 thinking points, one per line.</rule>
        <rule>Each point is about 14 to 16 words.</rule>
        <rule>Each point contains one concrete example (a situation, an object, a moment, or a type of person). A reflect prompt without an anchor fails.</rule>
        <rule>No platitudes, no fridge-magnet wisdom.</rule>
      </rules>
    </block>

  </section>

  <section id="7" name="Formatting rules">
    <rule id="1">Blank lines are meaningful. They separate logical sections within a block.</rule>
    <rule id="2">No trailing whitespace on any line.</rule>
    <rule id="3">No tabs. Spaces only.</rule>
    <rule id="4">No blank lines inside the body of @quote, @pause, or @estimate.</rule>
    <rule id="5">One blank line between the last content block and the next @package or @segment.</rule>
    <rule id="6">Properties (answer:, consequence:, correct_answers:, explanation:, hint:, true:, false:) are NOT declarations. They use "key: value" syntax with a colon and space.</rule>
  </section>

  <section id="8" name="Comments">
    <description>The .rlockie format supports full-line comments. Comments are a writer-only feature: the parser strips them before any other parsing happens, so they never reach the reader and never affect block boundaries, properties, or text segments.</description>

    <syntax>Any line whose first non-whitespace character is "#" is a comment.</syntax>

    <template>
# This is a comment. It will be stripped before parsing.
# Use it for notes, TODOs, draft markers, or to temporarily disable a swipe.

@text
First line of text.
    </template>

    <rules>
      <rule>A comment is recognised by its first non-whitespace character being "#". Leading whitespace before the "#" is allowed.</rule>
      <rule>Comments are FULL-LINE only. Inline comments (text followed by "#" on the same line) are NOT supported.</rule>
      <rule>Comments can sit anywhere in the file: between blocks, inside blocks, between properties, even between an answer: line and its consequence: line. The parser strips them before block splitting.</rule>
      <rule>To temporarily disable a swipe, prefix every line of the swipe (including the @declaration line) with "#".</rule>
      <rule>Comments do NOT count toward any length rule, swipe count, or character budget. They are invisible to the parser and to ReadlockFinalTest.xml.</rule>
      <rule>Comments are highlighted in the same muted grey (#9ca3af, italic) that property names (answer:, consequence:, hint:, explanation:) use, so comments sit quietly in the same visual register as format scaffolding rather than content.</rule>
    </rules>

    <example_use_cases>
      <case>Marking a draft section: <code># DRAFT, needs a stronger anchor in Phase 2</code></case>
      <case>Leaving a note for another writer: <code># Verify the 1990s ATM study citation before publishing</code></case>
      <case>Temporarily disabling a swipe by prefixing every line with "#".</case>
      <case>Explaining a non-obvious choice: <code># Using misconception-first intro here because the reader almost certainly believes the wrong picture</code></case>
    </example_use_cases>

    <mandatory_package_structure_comment>
      <description>Every @package MUST start with TWO comment lines. The first lists the swipe-type sequence; the second summarises the package's creative choices (Phase 2 variant, intro type, concept taught). Together they give a writer-facing index that makes both the shape AND the intent of the package visible at a glance before reading any content. Both comments are required for every package, in every course.</description>

      <placement>Both comment lines go IMMEDIATELY after the package title line (and after the "Free" line if the package is free), and BEFORE the first content block. Line 1 (swipe sequence) goes first, then line 2 (package summary) directly underneath.</placement>

      <line name="1" label="Swipe sequence">
        <syntax>A single line that begins with "#" and lists the swipe types (with the "@" prefix) separated by commas, in the order they appear inside the package. The list includes EVERY swipe: intro, stories, question, optional pause, reveal, optional estimate, true/false, optional reflect, outro.</syntax>
        <rules>
          <rule>The list lists swipe types in the same order they appear in the package body.</rule>
          <rule>Every swipe in the package appears in the list. The list length equals the swipe count.</rule>
          <rule>If the package uses an intro variant (skip-intro, quote intro, true/false intro, misconception-first), the swipe list reflects it. A quote intro starts with "@quote". A skip-intro package starts with "@text" (the first story).</rule>
        </rules>
      </line>

      <line name="2" label="Package summary">
        <syntax>A single line that begins with "#" and contains three comma-separated fields in this exact order: (1) Phase 2 variant letter with content descriptor in parentheses, (2) intro type, (3) "teaching: " followed by the concept name.</syntax>
        <rules>
          <rule>Field 1 format: "Variant X (descriptor)". X is A through G. The descriptor names what Phase 2 actually contains, not always "stories". Use the descriptor that matches the variant: Variant A = "N scenes", Variant B = "single narrative" or "N beats", Variant C = "N stories", Variant D = "N stories", Variant E = "N steps" or "mechanism walkthrough", Variant F = "historical arc", Variant G = "thought experiment". A package that does not literally contain stories must not say "stories".</rule>
          <rule>Field 2 values: "default intro" | "quote intro" | "true/false intro" | "misconception intro" | "skip intro". Exactly one of these.</rule>
          <rule>Field 3 format: "teaching: [concept name]" where the concept is the term that carries the green &lt;c:g&gt; highlight in Phase 4. Lowercase, no article, no quotes.</rule>
          <rule>Fields are separated by a comma and a single space. No em dashes, no semicolons.</rule>
        </rules>
      </line>

      <template>
@package
The Pretty Machine That Worked Better
Free
# @text, @text, @text, @question, @text, @true_false, @text
# Variant C (2 stories), default intro, teaching: the aesthetic-usability effect

@text
Two coffee makers sit on the same kitchen counter.
...
      </template>

      <rules>
        <rule>Both comment lines are required, not optional. Every package has both.</rule>
        <rule>The two comments are stripped by the parser before any other parsing, so they never reach the reader.</rule>
        <rule>A package missing either comment line is an error.</rule>
      </rules>

      <examples>
        <example label="Default spine, Variant C">
          <code># @text, @text, @text, @text, @question, @text, @true_false, @reflect, @text
# Variant C (3 stories), default intro, teaching: the habit loop</code>
          <description>Intro, three stories, question, reveal, true/false, reflect, outro. Phase 2 variant C (one extended case built across three swipes).</description>
        </example>
        <example label="Quote intro, Variant A">
          <code># @quote, @text, @text, @question, @text, @true_false, @text
# Variant A (2 stories), quote intro, teaching: the anchoring effect</code>
          <description>Quote intro, two reader-immersion stories, question, reveal, true/false, outro. Phase 6 reflect skipped.</description>
        </example>
        <example label="True/false intro, Variant E, Phase 5 empty">
          <code># @true_false, @text, @text, @question, @text, @text
# Variant E (2 stories), true/false intro, teaching: the power law</code>
          <description>True/false intro replaces Phase 5. Two experiment/findings stories, question, reveal, outro.</description>
        </example>
        <example label="Skip-intro, Variant D">
          <code># @text, @text, @text, @question, @pause, @text, @true_false, @reflect, @text
# Variant D (3 stories), skip intro, teaching: definite optimism</code>
          <description>Phase 1 intro skipped. Package opens directly at Phase 2 with three scenes showing the same pattern. Pause before the reveal.</description>
        </example>
        <example label="Misconception-first, Variant B">
          <code># @text, @text, @text, @question, @text, @true_false, @text
# Variant B (2 beats), misconception intro, teaching: the visceral level</code>
          <description>Misconception-first intro looks like a normal @text intro in line 1. The misconception is signalled inside the swipe by the &lt;c:r&gt; markup, and line 2 names it. Variant B is a single narrative, so the descriptor counts beats, not stories.</description>
        </example>
        <example label="Quote intro, Variant G">
          <code># @quote, @text, @text, @question, @text, @true_false, @text
# Variant G (thought experiment), quote intro, teaching: progressive disclosure</code>
          <description>Variant G builds the case from a hypothetical instead of stories. The descriptor is "thought experiment", never "N stories", because there are no characters or real scenes to count.</description>
        </example>
        <example label="Default intro, Variant F">
          <code># @text, @text, @text, @text, @question, @text, @true_false, @text
# Variant F (historical arc), default intro, teaching: the flywheel</code>
          <description>Variant F is one long story told across eras. The descriptor is "historical arc", not "3 stories", because it is one continuous arc split across swipes.</description>
        </example>
      </examples>
    </mandatory_package_structure_comment>
  </section>

</rlockie_format_guide>
